Take one more moment to look at this very nice diagram that lays it all out, and we will move on.
잠시 시간을 내서 이 멋진 도표를 보세요 모든 걸 배치한 거죠 그런 다음 넘어가죠
Now to the technicality that I wanted to mention.
이제 제가 말씀드리고 싶었던 세부적인 부분으로 넘어가죠
So I have been a bit loose in the past when I've said that the model predicts the next token, which
제가 비트를 좀 느슨하게 표현했는데요 모델이 다음 토큰을 예측한다고 했었죠 그렇게 생각할
is one way to think about it.
수도 있겠네요
One simple way to think about it.
간단하게 생각해 보죠
And we often use that, that turn of phrase, but it's not what's actually going on.
종종 그런 표현을 쓰지만 실제로는 그렇지 않아요
It's not like you have a transformer architecture and the bottom layer, what comes out of that is a
변압기 구조가 있는 것도 아니고 맨 아래 계층에서 나오는 건 단일 토큰이
single token, which is the predicted next token.
아니죠 예측 가능한 다음 토큰이요
That's not how it works.
그렇게 되는 게 아니에요
What actually comes out of the last layer is probabilities.
마지막 층에서 나오는 건 확률이에요
It has every single token, and for every token it has.
모든 토큰을 갖고 있고 그 모든 토큰에 대해 알고 있죠
What is the probability that that is the next token.
그게 다음 토큰이 될 확률은 얼마나 될까요?
It outputs that series of probabilities.
일련의 확률을 내놓죠
That's what comes out of the bottom of the neural network.
신경망 아래에서 나오는 거예요
And it's you may remember there was the last layer that we saw when we printed.
프린트할 때 마지막으로 봤던 레이어가 있었죠
The model is called LM Head.
LM 헤드라는 모델이에요
And that is really the very final step that comes out.
그게 가장 마지막 단계예요
It actually comes out with a vector of numbers that are known as the logits, which are the the that
숫자의 벡터인 로그잇을 가지고 나타납니다 확률을 나타내는
represent the probabilities.
것들이죠
And you need to put that through a function.
그걸 함수에 넣어야 해요 Put it up
Um, this is getting probably to too much detail now, but you may know it already.
너무 자세하게 설명하는 것 같지만 이미 알고 계실지도 몰라요
There's a function called softmax that converts these numbers into what can be thought of as probabilities,
소프트맥스라는 함수가 있는데 이 숫자들을 확률로 변환할 수 있습니다 각각의
because each each token will then be somewhere between 0 and 1, and they will all add up to one.
토큰은 0에서 1 사이일 것이고 그 다합이 1이기 때문이죠
So it gives you a way to interpret the results of the model as a probability of each possible next token.
따라서 모델의 결과를 가능한 다음 토큰의 확률로 해석할 수 있는 방법을 제공하죠
So that is actually what comes out of the forward pass.
이게 포워드 패스에서 나오는 거예요
Um, when you're doing inference when you're running this in inference mode, um, what you get out
추론 모드에서 이걸 실행하면 get-ference 모드에서 얻는 건
of it is then all of these probabilities.
이 모든 확률이에요
So what do you do with that.
이걸로 뭘 할 수 있을까요?
How do you how do you say what next token it's predicting?
다음 토큰이 뭘 예언하는지 어떻게 알죠?
Well, most of the time actually it's a very simple approach.
대부분은 아주 간단한 접근법이에요
You simply take the most likely next token.
가장 가능성이 높은 토큰을 선택하면 돼요
You take the token with the highest probability.
가능성이 높은 토큰을 선택하세요
It gave you all these different probabilities.
개연성이 아주 다양해요
Find out which one is the max.
누가 최대인지 알아봐요
Take that one as the next letter.
다음 글자는 이거로 해요
There are other techniques that are a little bit more sophisticated.
좀 더 세련된 비트도 있어요
You can sample randomly using these probabilities as your as your weight for how you sample.
이런 확률을 체중으로 삼아 무작위로 샘플을 채취할 수 있어요
And that gives you a bit more variety.
비트가 좀 더 다양해지죠
And there are some other techniques you can use to sample a few letters in a row, and then decide whether
몇 개의 글자를 연속해서 샘플링할 수 있는 다른 기술도 있어요 그리고 그 경로를
that's the path that you want to take.
선택할 수 있죠
So there are a bunch of different strategies during inference that you can use based on these probabilities
추론할 때 다양한 전략을 쓸 수 있어요 이런 확률을 바탕으로 최선의 결과를
to do the best job.
낼 수 있죠
And in fact, when we go and look in our project in a second, we are going to use a slightly non-standard
잠시 후 우리 프로젝트를 보면 약간 비표준 전략을 사용할
strategy, since we know that each that this token represents a cost, it represents a number.
겁니다 각각의 토큰은 비용, 숫자를 나타내니까요
We can do something a little bit smart with it, but but that's not necessary.
비트를 좀 더 영리하게 바꿀 수도 있지만 그럴 필요는 없어요
You can also always just simply pick pick the one with the highest probability.
아니면 가장 가능성이 높은 걸 선택해도 되고요
So that's model output really explained.
모델 출력이 잘 설명했고요
I hope that's now crystal clear for you.
이제 확실히 아셨길 바라요
Um, and then the loss function.
그리고 상실 함수요
So I slightly glossed over in the last video.
지난 영상에서는 살짝 얼버무렸어요
Like you calculate a loss.
손해 보는 것도 모르시네요
How bad was it?
얼마나 심각했어요?
So what does that actually mean in practice?
실제론 어떤 의미일까요?
It's wonderfully simple.
놀랍도록 간단해요
So we've got these probabilities of all of the possible next tokens.
가능한 다음 토큰의 모든 가능성을 갖고 있죠
So what you do is you say okay, well we actually know what the next token was supposed to be.
그래서 다음 토큰이 무엇이었는지 알고 있다고 하는 거죠
Let's say it was supposed to be 99.
99개라고 가정해 보죠
So you look up in all of these probabilities and you say, what probability did the model give for 99
이 모든 확률을 살펴보고 모델에서 99의 확률을 계산해 올바른 다음 토큰이
for the thing that actually was the right next token.
무엇인지 알아내는 거죠
And that's all that matters here.
그게 가장 중요하죠
All that matters is what probability did it give to the thing that was actually correct.
중요한 건 정확한 결과를 낼 확률이 얼마냐는 거죠
Um, if it gives if it gave that a 100% probability, then it was perfect.
만약 그게 100%의 확률이라면 완벽한 거죠
It was 100% confident in the right results.
좋은 결과를 낼 거라고 100% 확신했어요
And everything else would have to be zero because probabilities will add up to one.
다른 건 다 0이어야 해요 확률은 1이 되니까요
So so that would be absolutely perfect.
그러니 정말 완벽하죠
If it's anything less than 100%, then it didn't do well.
만약 100% less라면 잘 안 된 거예요
And the you know, the lower probability it gave, the worse it did.
확률이 낮을수록 더 안 좋은 결과가 나왔어요
And so you take that probability and then it just turns out that the formula that seems to work well
그 확률을 따져보면 잘 되는 것 같은 공식은 그 숫자의
is to take the log of that number and then negate it.
로그를 반증하는 거예요
So you take minus one times the log of that number.
1을 그 숫자의 로그에 곱해요
And if you work that out, that means that if that number is one, if it's 100% probability, then you
이것을 계산하면, 만약 1이라면, 100%의 확률이라면, 0이
get zero.
되겠죠.
And that's sounds good because you want zero loss.
손해 볼 게 없으니 좋은 거죠
Loss should be nothing if you were perfect.
완벽하다면 패배는 아무것도 아니죠
And then the lower your probability is, the worse the higher that loss number will be.
확률이 낮을수록 손실률도 높아지는 거죠
So taking negative log of the probability, um, is a way of of having a good, well well-behaving loss
확률을 부정적으로 기록하는 건 손실 함수를 잘 활용하는 방법이죠
And there's a fancy name for it.
거창한 명칭도 있죠
This loss function is known as the cross entropy loss.
이 손실 함수를 교차 엔트로피 손실이라고 해요
That's what they call it.
그렇게 부르더군요
It's just negative log of the probability of the true next token.
다음 토큰의 참일 확률의 마이너스 로그일 뿐이죠
And that's, that's what's used.
그걸 사용했어요
Um, and that's that's what's being used right now if your training is going on, it is calculating
훈련을 계속한다면 지금 그걸 이용하는 거예요 각 예측의
the cross entropy loss for each of the predictions.
교차 엔트로피 손실을 계산하는 거죠
And there's a there's another side note.
그리고 덧붙일 말이 있어요
There's an The interpretation of this for particularly for data scientists amongst you, this is the
이것에 대한 해석이 있어요 특히 데이터 과학자들에겐요
calculation that's used for classification when you're trying to classify something into different bins.
이건 분류에 사용되는 계산입니다 뭔가를 다른 빈으로 분류하려고 할 때요
If you've got like back in the day when there were times when we were trying to classify images to be
예전에 이미지를 4-5가지 다른 범주로 분류하려고 했던 때가
one of 4 or 5 different categories, cross-entropy loss, you come up with a probability and you use
있었죠 교차 엔트로피 손실요 확률을 생각해내고 교차 엔트로피
cross-entropy loss to figure out whether or not you've done a good job of classification.
손실을 이용해서 분류를 잘했는지 아닌지 알아내요
And in fact, that makes sense, because the whole process of predicting the next token is really a
사실, 말이 되는 것이 다음 토큰을 예측하는 전체 프로세스는 분류 문제이기
classification problem.
때문이죠
You're just trying to say there are many possible categories that this next token could be.
다음 토큰이 될 수 있는 카테고리는 아주 많다는 거죠?
In fact, there's the entire all of the possible next tokens.
사실, 가능한 모든 다음 패가 거기 있어요
And we're going to predict which one is the most likely bucket to to put for the next token.
어떤 버킷이 다음 토큰에 가장 잘 맞을지 예측하는 거죠.
And so the whole process of generative AI is really just a classification problem.
따라서 인공지능이 생성되는 과정은 사실 분류 문제일 뿐이에요
Classifying the next token, figuring out the probability that the next token is what it turns out to
다음 토큰을 분류하고 다음 토큰이 무엇인지 밝혀질 확률을 계산하는
be.
거죠
And so interestingly, for our particular project for predicting model prices, it's really, as I said
흥미롭게도 우리 프로젝트의 가격 예측은 몇 년 전에 말씀드렸듯이 정말
some time ago, it's really a regression problem.
퇴보하고 있어요
You're trying to predict a number and we're treating it like a classification problem, which is okay,
숫자를 예측하려 하고 분류 문제로 취급하는 거죠 그건 괜찮아요
because it's really going to turn out to be just a number between 0 and 999, which, sorry, between
왜냐하면 0과 999 사이의 숫자가 될 테니까요 죄송합니다 1과 999
1 and 999, which are just 999 different possible buckets.
사이 가능한 999개의 양동이들이죠
And we're just trying to classify effectively every product into one of these 999 buckets.
모든 제품을 이 999개의 양동이에 효과적으로 분류하려는 거예요
And that's why it works quite well as a classification problem.
그래서 분류 문제로서 꽤 효과적인 거죠
And it's why the frontier models are good at it and why we're hoping, fingers crossed, that our open
그래서 개척 모델들이 잘 되고 있고 우리의 오픈 소스 모델도
source model is going to be good at it too.
잘 되길 바라는 거죠
And with all of this, some good useful theory behind us.
이 모든 걸 종합해 보면 유용한 이론이 뒷받침되겠죠
But now it's time to get back to some practice.
하지만 지금은 다시 연습할 때예요 get get it
So with that in mind, it's time for us to talk about how has our open source, uh, fine tuning been
그걸 염두에 두고 오픈 소스 미세 조정은 어떻게 돼가는지 얘기해보죠